Fletcher Pratt Papers
Fletcher Pratt Papers
ca. 1935-1955?
Pratt, Fletcher, 1897-1956.
18 cartons
Correspondence, manuscripts of the American military, naval, and science fiction novelist.
2578780
Biographical History
Fletcher Pratt (1897-1956) was an American military, naval, and science fiction novelist. Born in Buffalo, New York, Pratt is said to have been raised on an Indian reservation. He attended Hobart College for a year. During World War I he served with the War Library Service. During his intensive writing career, Pratt wrote chiefly on military and naval subjects, but also in the field of science fiction, collaborating often with L. Sprague DeCamp.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Fletcher Pratt Papers consists of correspondence-subject files, manuscripts and research material, and a small amount of printed material and memorabila. Correspondence is primarily with publications ( Atlanta Journal, Fantasy and Science Fiction, Harper's Magazine, The Infantry Journal, Pacific Spectator) and publishers (Ballantine Books, Bobbs-Merrill, Doubleday & Company, Gnome Press, Henry Holt and Company, Penguin) but also includes a few organizations (e.g., Science Fiction League of America). Subject files cover miscellaneous topics, most relating to either the Navy (British Navy at War, First Philippine Sea, 4th Fleet, German Navy) or general military (Eleven Generals, Macarthur, Munitions and equipment, Pearl Harbor, Spies/espionage). Manuscripts and research material contains material for more than 150 articles, essays, stories, and other pieces of writing by Pratt, as well as a small amount of printed material (book reviews, published stories and similar). Memorabilia contains clippings and nine scrapbooks.
Arrangement of the Collection
All series are arranged alphabetically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Military history; Science fiction; Pratt, Fletcher, 1897-1956.; American literature -- 20th century.; Authors, American.; Military art and science in literature.; Military history in literature.; Novelists, American.; Science fiction, American.; Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Research notes.; Scrapbooks.; Authors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of John D. Clark, 1970.
Inventory
- Biographical
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General A-G (Box 1)
  - General H-Z (Box 1)
  - Harry Altshuler (Author's Agent) (Box 1)
  - American Broadcasting Company (Box 1)
  - American magazines, lists of stories sold with date and topic, sorted by title of magazine (e.g. Atlantic Monthly, Colliers, etc.); 2 folders (Box 1)
  - American Mercury (Box 1)
  - Atlanta Journal (Box 1)
  - Ballantine Books (Box 1)
  - Bobbs-Merrill Company (Box 1)
  - Bread Loaf
    - Correspondence/ conference schedules/ address lists (Box 1)
    - The Crumb (Box 1)
    - Drawings/ Creative writings, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Writer's Conference (Middlebury College Bulletin) (Box 1)
  - Charles Scribner's Sons (Box 1)
  - Civil War Round Table (blank letters and envelopes) (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - "Kicks and Kurses" (Box 1)
    - Navy Department (Box 1)
    - "Nut Letters" and a Ginkgo leaf from 1951 (Box 1)
    - Secretary of the Navy (Box 1)
  - Coward-McCann, Inc. (Box 1)
  - Curtis Brown, Ltd. (Box 1)
  - Memorandums (Box 1)
  - Bernard DeVoto (Box 1)
  - Doubleday & Company, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Duell, Sloan & Pearce, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Detective Stories (Box 2)
  - Fantasia (Box 2)
  - Fantasy and Science Fiction (Box 2)
  - Funk & Wagnall's Company (Box 2)
  - Gnome Press (Box 2)
  - Green Leaf Publishing Co. (Box 2)
  - Guggenheimer & Untermyer (Box 2)
  - Harcourt, Brace and Company, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Harper's Magazine (Box 2)
  - Harper and Brothers Publishers (Box 2)
  - Harrison-Hilton Books (Box 2)
  - Harrison Smith and Robert Haas, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Hawthorn Books Inc, Publishers (Box 2)
  - Henry Holt and Company, Inc. (Box 2)
  - The Infantry Journal (Box 2)
  - Journal and Sentinel (Box 2)
  - Little, Brown & Company (Box 2)
  - The Lotos Club (Box 2)
  - Macmillan Company (Box 2)
  - Maps, charts, and Naval photographs, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - National Better Business Bureau (Box 2)
  - New York Author's Club (Box 2)
  - Otis Kline Associates, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Pacific Spectator (Box 2)
  - Penguin Books (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Pratt alone (Box 2)
    - Pratt with others (Box 2)
    - Mrs. F. Pratt (Box 2)
  - Pratt (book covers) (Box 2)
  - Prime Press (Box 2)
  - RKO Radiopictures, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Random House (Box 2)
  - Reviews (written in German) (Box 2)
  - Rinehart & Company, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Robert Hale Limited (Box 2)
  - Science Fiction League of America (Box 2)
  - Smith & Durrell, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Stellar Publishing Corporation (Box 2)
  - Street and Smith Publications, Inc. (Box 2)
  - Twayne Publishers (Box 2)
  - Vanguard Press Inc. (Box 2)
  - Viking Press Inc.-Publishers (Box 2)
  - W.W. Norton & Company (Box 2)
  - William Sloan Associates (Box 2)
  - Yale University Press (Box 2)
  - Ziff-Davis Publishing Company (Box 2)
- Subject files
  - Aleutians (Box 3)
  - Army - U.S. History (Box 3)
  - Bases (Box 3)
  - Bismarck Sea (Box 3)
  - Bonins Operations (Box 3)
  - Borneo (Box 3)
  - "The British Navy at War" (Box 3)
  - Casablanca (Box 3)
  - Office of Censorship (and related papers) (Box 3)
  - Central Pacific (Box 3)
  - Communications (Box 3)
  - Coral Sea (Box 3)
  - "Desron 23" (Box 3)
  - "Eleven Generals" (Box 3)
  - Esquire Articles (Box 3)
  - First Philippine Sea (Box 3)
  - "4th Fleet" (Box 3)
  - Freak Weapons (Box 3)
  - German Navy (Box 3)
  - "Hollywood Squadron" (Box 3)
  - Italy/ Sicily (Box 3)
  - Interview with Pratt (Box 3)
  - Japanese Navy (Box 3)
  - Kwajalein (Central Pacific) (Box 3)
  - Leyte Gulf (Box 3)
  - Luzon (Box 3)
  - MacArthur
    - AREA (Box 3)
    - Command (Box 3)
    - Halsey (Box 3)
    - Offensive (Box 3)
  - Magazine articles (Box 3)
  - Marianas/ Saipan (Box 3)
  - Marshall and Gilbert (Box 3)
  - Mediterranean (Box 3)
  - Midway (Box 3)
  - Munitions and Equipment (Box 4)
  - Naval Africa (Box 4)
  - "The Navy" (Box 4)
  - Navy Department Communiqués
    - #8-117 (incomplete run), 2/16/41- 9/3/42 (Box 4)
    - #301- 400, 3/6/43-6/3/43 (Box 4)
    - #401- 500, 6/4/43 (Box 4)
    - #501- 539, 541-582, 2/4/44- 3/1/45 (Box 4)
  - Navy Personnel
    - Admiral Halsey (Box 4)
    - Admiral Nimitz (Box 4)
    - Admirals (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous Officers (Box 4)
  - Navy - Italy, France, Sweden, Russia (Box 4)
  - Navy - U.S. History, 3 folders (Box 4)
  - "The Navy's War" (Box 4)
  - New Guinea (Box 4)
  - New Ireland (Box 4)
  - Normandy (Box 4)
  - Okinawa (Box 4)
  - "Ordeal by Fire" (Box 4)
  - Paramushiru (Box 4)
  - Pearl Harbor (Box 4)
  - Propaganda (Box 4)
  - Salt Lake City (Box 4)
  - SAVO Island (Box 4)
  - Solomons
    - "Solomons" (Box 4)
    - "Battle of Cape Esperance" (Box 4)
    - "Battle of Guadalcanal" (Box 4)
    - "Battle of Santa Cruz" (Box 4)
  - Spies/ Espionage (Box 5)
  - Stanton (Box 5)
  - SUBS
    - Atlantic (Box 5)
    - Mines (Box 5)
    - Pacific (Box 5)
  - U.S.S. Biloxi (Box 5)
  - U.S.S. Salt Lake City (Box 5)
  - World War I (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous unsorted, 5 folders (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous unsorted, 9 folders (Box 6)
  - Legal material- Pratt vs. Future Publications, Inc., and John Raymond (Box 6)
- Manuscripts and research material
  - Aaron Wand and The Picket Line (Box 7)
  - Adventure of Joshua Barney (Box 7)
  - All About Rockets and Jets (Box 7)
  - Another Trafalgar (Box 7)
  - Atom Submarine and Her Skipper (Box 7)
  - Atoms, Matter, and Energy (Box 7)
  - Battles That Changed History, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Bell, Book and Candle (Box 7)
  - Best Reported War in History (Box 7)
  - Big Pacific Push (Box 7)
  - Blood on the Ground (Box 7)
  - Blood, Sweet Blood (Box 7)
  - Book of Famous and Decisive Battles, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews (Box 7)
  - Boyle of the Chasseur (Box 7)
  - Building of the Atom Submarine (Box 7)
  - Burp in Time (Box 7)
  - CA 25 (Box 7)
  - Campaign Beyond Glory (Box 7)
  - Campaign in the Coral Sea (Box 7)
  - Campaign in the Java Sea (Box 7)
  - Captain Who Tried to Sell His Ship (Box 7)
  - Cards are Dealt (Box 7)
  - Carnelian Cube - galleys, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Caribbean Command (Box 7)
  - Case of the 14m man (Box 8)
  - Castles of Chron (Box 8)
  - Chance for a Piece of Change (Box 8)
  - Chinese Invention (Box 8)
  - City of the Living Dead, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Civil War, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Civil War in Pictures (text) (Box 8)
  - Code Experts War, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - [Collected Pratt science fiction] (Box 8)
  - Comic Strips (Box 8)
  - Compact History of the United States Navy, 3 folders (Box 8)
  - Crisis of the Computers (Box 9)
  - Curious Literature of the Comic Strips (Box 9)
  - Current Post-War Naval Developments (Box 9)
  - Dr. Grimshaw's Sanitarium (Box 9)
  - Double Jeopardy, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Elemental Question (Box 9)
  - Eleven Generals, 2 folders (Box 9)
  - Engineers From Europe (Box 9)
  - Estimate of the Situation (Box 9)
  - Facts of Soviet Espionage (outline) (Box 9)
  - Famous Inventors and Their Inventions (Box 9)
  - Fighting Machine (Box 9)
  - First of the Great Raids (Box 9)
  - Frost and Her Playmates (Box 9)
  - Future of Cities (outline) (Box 9)
  - Gavagan's Bar (Box 9)
  - General Can't Write English (Box 9)
  - Goodbye Street (Box 9)
  - Great Steel Panic (Box 9)
  - Green Thumb (Box 9)
  - Grift Goes Legitimate (Box 9)
  - Hail Caesar (Box 9)
  - Harold Shea, 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Here, Putzi! (Box 9)
  - Heroic Years (Box 9)
  - History of the South Atlantic Campaign (Box 10)
  - How the Censor Rigged the News (Box 10)
  - Interviews (notes) with Pacific Fleet Personnel (Box 10)
  - Invention of the Atomic Submarine (Box 10)
  - Inventions (Box 10)
  - Is the Navy Ready? (Box 10)
  - January Easy Chair, by Bernard DeVoto (Box 10)
  - Keyport Auction (outline) (Box 10)
  - Lament of Lamethenon (Box 10)
  - Lantflex and the Lost Plane (Box 10)
  - Longview (Box 10)
  - Loss of the Wasp (Box 10)
  - Lost Battalion, includes mimeographed script for radio adaptation on WNYC, 13 Apr 1938 (Box 10)
  - Mad Destroyer (Box 10)
  - Man Who Awoke (Box 10)
  - Man Who Never Lived (Box 10)
  - Man Who Pulls the Trigger (Box 10)
  - Man With a Million Dollars Cash (Box 10)
  - Mathematics of Magic (Box 10)
  - Military and Naval History of the United States, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Military Genius of Abraham Lincoln (preface) (Box 10)
  - Moon and I (Box 10)
  - Monitor and the Merimac (Box 10)
  - Most Important Job in the Navy (Box 10)
  - Mutinies in Foreign Navies (Box 10)
  - Mysteries of Midway (Box 10)
  - Mystery of the Hittitis (Box 10)
  - Napoleon- research notes (Box 10)
  - Napoleon- research notes, 4 folders (Box 11)
  - Napoleon, 2 folders (Box 11)
  - [Naval aviation book], 3 folders (Box 11)
  - Naval History of the Civil War (outline, research) (Box 11)
  - Navy Has Wings (Box 12)
  - Nightwork, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - No Pity for Heroes, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Obscene Language is Not Necessary for Realism (Box 12)
  - Oh, Say Can You See (Box 12)
  - One Destroyer (Box 12)
  - One Man's Meat (Box 12)
  - One-Ship Fleet (Box 12)
  - Ordeal by Fire, 3 folders (Box 12)
  - Ordeal by Fire (television adaptation) (Box 12)
  - Our New Navy (Box 12)
  - Palimpsest of St. Augustine (Box 12)
  - Pardon My Mistake (Box 12)
  - Pattern Repeat (Box 12)
  - Pictorial History of the Civil War (Box 12)
  - Planet Lithia (Box 12)
  - Preble's Boys, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Preble's Boys-notes, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Preble's Boys-notes, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Red King, 3 folders (Box 13)
  - Reign of the Navy (Box 13)
  - Revenge (Box 13)
  - Rhodes, a Study in Sea Power (Box 13)
  - Road to Empire - correspondences (Box 13)
  - Roaring Trumpet (Box 13)
  - Roger Bacon Formula (Box 13)
  - Roger's Reef, by John T. Goodrich (Box 13)
  - Scientific Articles (Box 13)
  - Sea Power and Today's War (Box 13)
  - Second Chance (Box 13)
  - Secret and Urgent, 2 folders (Box 13)
  - Seed From Space (Box 13)
  - Ship That Could Shoot (Box 13)
  - Ship That Fought the War (Box 13)
  - Ship That Made Like a Fleet (Box 13)
  - Should Human Population Increase Be Controlled? (Box 13)
  - Silver Accident (outline) (Box 13)
  - Square-Cube Law (Box 13)
  - Stanton: Lincoln's Secretary of War, 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Strange Deed of Captain Glenney (Box 14)
  - Submarine is on the Ropes (Box 14)
  - Submarines Pacific (Box 14)
  - Super-Carrier Forrestad (Box 14)
  - Superstitions in Sports (Box 14)
  - Symbiosis (Box 14)
  - Thing in the Woods (Box 14)
  - Third King, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Three Kings - notes (Box 14)
  - This was Trafalgar (Box 14)
  - Three Valdemars (Box 14)
  - Turkey-shoot of Saipan (Box 14)
  - Twilight of the Ideals, 2 folders (Box 14)
  - Undying Fire (Box 14)
  - Unexpected Planet (Box 14)
  - United States Navy History-Revolution (Box 15)
  - United States Navy History-WWI-press stories (Box 15)
  - Violation of Rules (Box 15)
  - Wall of Serpents (Box 15)
  - Wanderer's Return (Box 15)
  - War of the Giants (Box 15)
  - War on Western Waters (Box 15)
  - Weissenbroch Spectacles (Box 15)
  - What Happened to Cicero? (Box 15)
  - Who Gave Their Lives? (Box 15)
  - Who Pays For It? (Box 15)
  - World Around the Corner (Box 15)
  - World War II and the Changing Conception of Sea Power (Box 15)
  - [Untitled science-fiction collection] (Box 15)
  - [Unidentified], 6 folders (Box 15)
  - Printed Material (Box 15)
    - Book reviews (Box 15)
    - Civil War (Box 15)
    - Foreign Language editions (Box 15)
    - Infantry Journal (4 issues) (Box 15)
    - New Jersey (Box 15)
  - Pratt prints from Pacific Spectator (Box 16)
  - Pratt prints from U.S. Naval Institution Proceedings (Box 16)
  - Pratt stories from Harper's (Box 16)
  - "Roundup of the Fleet", Our Navy (Box 16)
  - "Roundup on the War", Our Navy (Box 16)
  - Science Fiction, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - World War II, 5 folders (Box 16)
  - [Unsorted manuscripts], 3 folders (Box 16)
- Memorabilia
  - Miscellaneous personal items, "Regulations for Correspondents Accompanying U.S. Army Forces in the Field"; humorous song about DESRON 23; story about the Rawalpindi; etc. (Box 17)
  - Newspaper clippings, includes press releases from US military, book reviews, etc.; 14 folders (Box 17)
  - Scrapbooks
    Pages of all scrapbooks are EXTREMELY brittle. Handle as little, and as carefully, as possible.
    - "GIMMI 88", 1929-1930; newspaper clippings, notes, cartoons, correspondence, etc. relating to a card game released by Katagiri Brothers, similar to bridge, called "Gimmi-88" or "Hachi-hachi" (Box 17)
    - Clippings of reviews of Pratt's books, 1941-1943; 1 volume (Oversize 1)
    - Clippings of articles by Pratt for the New York Post, 1939-1940; 1 volume (Oversize 2)
    - Clippings of reviews of Pratt's books, 1935-1940; 2 volumes (Oversize 3)
    - Miscellaneous scrapbooks, 6 volumes (Box 18)